Chapter four. First models.
In this lesson, we will treat the first model as a
professional instrument, not a warm-up exercise.
A beginner often asks, what model should I use?
A professional asks a sharper question: what have I
learned from the simplest model that could possibly work?
That first model gives us a reference point.
Without it, we cannot honestly say what complexity is
buying.
Here is the professional question. Not, can we train a
powerful model.
The question is, what decision improves because this model
exists?
A first model gives the team a measurement baseline. It
also gives the team a shared language.
Product can ask whether the prediction changes the
customer experience.
Operations can ask whether the prediction changes
intervention timing.
Engineering can ask whether the improvement is worth the
serving cost.
That is how model choice moves from taste into evidence.
This lesson is baseline discipline.
A naive baseline shows what happens when we barely model
anything.
An interpretable baseline lets the data speak through a
simple structure.
A richer model comes later, only after the simple model
reveals what it can and cannot explain.
This ladder is important because each step earns the next.
If a linear model already solves the business problem, a
neural network may add cost without adding value.
If the simple model fails in clear ways, those failures
tell us what to try next.
Our case is delivery-time prediction. At dispatch time, we
estimate when the order will arrive.
That supports customer communication and late-delivery
intervention.
This is important because the model is not just predicting
a number.
It is shaping expectations, staffing decisions, and
escalation workflows.
If the estimate is too optimistic, customers become
frustrated.
If it is too pessimistic, the business may over-correct
and waste operational attention.
So even in a small example, the prediction sits inside a
real decision loop.
The prediction moment matters.
At dispatch time, the model may know distance, preparation
time, courier load, weather, and rush hour.
It may not know anything that happens after delivery.
This single boundary prevents many accidental leakage
problems.
For example, if we accidentally include the actual arrival
delay, or a support ticket created after the delivery, the
model may look amazing offline and fail in production.
A first model should make this boundary explicit before
training starts.
The dataset is intentionally small and inspectable. Each
row is a past delivery.
The target is total delivery minutes. The features are
simple operational signals.
This is a good first-model setup because a learner can
reason about every input.
Distance should usually increase time. Bad weather should
usually increase time.
Rush hour should usually increase time.
When a feature has an unexpected direction, that does not
automatically mean the model is wrong, but it gives us a
concrete question to investigate.
Before training, we ask three leakage questions. Would
this feature be known at prediction time?
Was the label created after the outcome? Did train and
test share future information?
A simple first model makes suspicious results easier to
notice.
If the first model is unbelievably accurate, we should not
celebrate immediately.
We should ask whether the data split, timestamp logic, or
feature pipeline accidentally gave the model information
from the future.
Now run the local example. The goal is not scale; it is
judgment.
We compare a naive mean baseline with linear regression on
the same delivery-time task.
Both models see the same split and the same metric, so the
comparison is fair.
This is the habit to copy in real work: keep the data,
metric, and evaluation window fixed while the model
changes.
The naive baseline predicts the average delivery time.
It ignores distance, weather, courier load, and rush hour.
That sounds weak, but it answers an essential question.
How much error exists before the model learns any
structure?
This number protects us from self-deception.
If a fancy model barely beats the average, then the model
may be impressive technically but weak for this decision.
Next we train a linear regression baseline.
It is still simple, but now the model can use structure.
It can learn that distance, weather, and rush hour change
expected time.
The value is that performance and explanation remain
inspectable. Training is fast.
Serving is cheap. The coefficients can be read by a human.
For many production problems, that combination is not a
compromise; it is a serious engineering advantage.
Here is the key result. The naive mean baseline has mean
absolute error nine point one two.
Linear regression drops it to one point nine four. That is
not a small cosmetic improvement.
It is evidence that the simple operational features
contain usable structure.
Mean absolute error is easy to explain: on average, how
many minutes are we wrong?
So the improvement is not just a leaderboard number.
It translates into a much tighter estimate for the people
using the system.
We can inspect the learned weights.
Distance, weather severity, and rush hour all push
delivery time upward.
That direction makes operational sense.
The negative preparation-time weight deserves review,
because it may reflect process timing or dataset quirks.
Interpretability helps us find those questions early.
This is why simple models are not only for beginners.
A professional engineer uses them to find bugs,
assumptions, and business questions before the system
becomes harder to understand.
Now use the ML Baseline Builder skill.
It forces us to name the metric, the evidence, and the
next justified escalation.
Instead of saying, the score looks good, we ask what the
score proves, what it does not prove, and whether a richer
model is justified.
For this case, the skill should point out that the linear
baseline is meaningfully better than naive, but it has not
yet proven robustness across restaurants, weather
conditions, or courier-load extremes.
After the first model, do not jump straight to a bigger
model. Check error slices.
Inspect outliers. Test whether predictions are calibrated
enough for decisions.
Review leakage again. Only then should we try richer trees
or ensembles.
A decision gate is not a delay tactic.
It is how we avoid spending a week on complexity when the
next useful action is a one-hour data review.
Here are common mistakes. Skipping the naive baseline.
Changing the metric between models.
Celebrating only the aggregate score. Ignoring slice
failures.
Explaining results after the model has already been
chosen.
First-model discipline protects us from all five. The
danger is not simplicity.
The danger is unmeasured complexity, where the team cannot
tell whether a larger model improved the decision or
merely made the pipeline harder to reason about.
Your practice task is simple. Choose one prediction
moment. Write one naive baseline.
Train one interpretable baseline. Compare one metric.
Review one failure slice.
Then ask the professional question: what did complexity
buy?
If you can answer that clearly, you are not just running
machine learning code.
You are building engineering judgment that transfers to
fraud detection, recommendation, search, forecasting, and
almost every applied machine learning system.
The goal is not to stay simple forever. The goal is to
know what complexity buys.
A first model should teach you something before a larger
model enters the room.
Keep one sentence from this chapter: complexity should
earn its place.
In the next lessons, that sentence will guide how we
evaluate models, diagnose failures, and decide when a more
powerful method is truly worth it.